Guide to the Henry R. Luce Papers 1894-2004 (bulk, 1932-1967) MS 3014
New-York Historical Society
Henry R. Luce papers
1894-2004 (bulk, 1932-1967)
New-York Historical Society
Grover, Allen, 1900-1993
Time, inc.
Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987
MS 3014
101.2 Linear feet in 205 boxes of various sizes and 13 folders with oversize materials.
The Henry R. Luce papers include documents related to Luce's personal and professional life and highlight his legacy as a major publisher and an active participant in the public affairs of the 20th century. Files with correspondence, memoranda and printed materials from and about publishers, members of the clergy, politicians, businessmen, editors, journalists, syndicated columnists, ambassadors, military officers and generals, foreign dignitaries and other individuals make up a large portion of the collection. In addition there are original drafts and final versions of articles and speeches; letters to his parents and siblings; trip files; reel audio tape recordings; financial files; and photographs. There are also Time Inc. memoranda dealing with editorial policy, personnel, management, and publishing. Some of the records are those of Clare Boothe Luce, the wife of HRL, and Allen Grover, HRL's personal assistant. Subjects frequently addressed include international relations, Communism, the rule of law, Luce's vision for the United States, the mission of the press, China, economics, and private enterprise.
Arrangement Note
Overall Organization
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series I. Biographical and Subject Files, 1916-2004 (bulk, 1930-1967)
Series II. Speeches and Writings, 1916-1967 (bulk, 1930-1966)
Series III. Notable Memoranda, 1931-1967
Series IV. Family Correspondence and School Records, 1898-1973 (bulk, 1898-1948)
Series V. Subject Name Files, 1894-1995 (bulk 1933-1967)
Series VI. Allen Grover Files, 1933-1961 (bulk 1938-1959)
Series VII. Clare Boothe Luce Subject Files, circa 1925?-1995 (bulk 1935-1975)
Series VIII. Financial Files, 1933-1963
Series IX. Photographs, circa 1897?-2001 (bulk 1900-1967)
Specific Notes
With minor exceptions, the collection follows original order with most of the original folder titles having been retained.
The term "includes," when used at the file level, indicates that the item(s) mentioned are just some of the things found in the indicated folder. The term "contains," when used at the file level, indicates that the item(s) described constitute the entire content of the indicated folder.
Box numbers prefaced with "RC" indicate a record carton and those prefaced with "FF" indicate flat files.
Administrative History
Henry R. Luce (hereafter HRL) directed that all his files before 1933 be thrown out when his new secretary, Corinne Thrasher, arrived and found them unmanageable, leaving a relatively small number of records in his papers prior to the 1930s. Upon his death in 1967, HRL's remaining files and those of his personal assistants were reviewed item by item and divided into records classified as personal and business. Records classified as business became part of the Time Inc. archives while those considered personal became part of the Henry R. Luce papers. In the initial division the personal papers included correspondence pertaining to HRL's outside interests and activities, family correspondence and personal correspondence with outsiders, as well as photographs and financial records. Some of his files during the division were given to the Library of Congress with copies of the more prominent records retained in his papers. The arrangement of the papers was partially determined by the needs of Robert Elson who was given the task of writing a corporate history of Time Inc. Between 1967 and early 2000s additional materials were added to the collection.
(The above note was based on information found in Series I, folder "Files and Personal Papers of HRL.")
Biographical Note
Henry Robinson Luce (hereafter HRL) was born on 3 April 1898 in Tengchow (currently Penglai), China to Presbyterian missionaries Reverend Dr. Henry Winters Luce (1868-1941) and Elizabeth Middleton Luce (1870-1948). HRL spent the first 14 years of his life in China, apart from a visit to the United States in 1906-1907. He attended Chefoo School, a British run preparatory institution in northern China. In 1912, when he was 14, HRL travelled to England to briefly study in St. Albans School, before returning to the U.S. and entering the Hotchkiss School in Lakeville, Connecticut the following year.
In 1916 HRL began attending Yale University where he served as managing editor of the Yale Daily News and actively contributed to other university publications. A member of the Yale ROTC Field Artillery Unit, he left college to train army recruits during World War I and was discharged as Second Lieutenant at the end of 1918. Returning to Yale, he graduated in 1920.
Following graduation, HRL spent a year studying history at Oxford University, coming back to the United States in 1921 to take a job as a cub reporter at the Chicago Daily News and then the Baltimore News. HRL quit his job in 1922 to concentrate on the creation of a "news-magazine" with Briton Hadden, a classmate from Hotchkiss and Yale. Together they formed the company Time Incorporated (later changed to Time Inc.) and published the first issue of their magazine, TIME, in New York in 1923.
On 22 December 1923 HRL married Lila Ross Hotz (1899-1999), the couple having two sons: Henry Luce III in 1925 and Peter Paul Luce in 1928. After briefly moving to live in Cleveland, Ohio in 1925, along with the publishing operations of TIME, HRL moved back to New York in 1927. Following Hadden's death in 1929, HRL became the sole head of Time Inc., launching additional ventures throughout the 1930s, including FORTUNE in 1930, THE MARCH OF TIME radio series in 1931 (and short film series in 1935), and LIFE in 1936. HRL divorced Lila Hotz in 1935, marrying Clare Boothe Brokaw (1903-1987), a playwright and former managing editor of Vanity Fair, the same year.
As a prominent publisher, HRL corresponded with a large number of individuals, including politicians, educators, and businessmen. He traveled extensively, both nationally and internationally, and was frequently invited to speak before professional, academic and church groups. In the early years of World War II, as a member of the Century Group, HRL advocated providing assistance to Great Britain, envisioning an expanded global role for the United States after the conclusion of the war. His vision was laid out in his best known article "The American Century," published in LIFE in 1941.
HRL's increasing interest in politics and world affairs led to his involvement in the 1940 presidential campaign where he served as one of the driving forces promoting the candidacy of Wendell Willkie, the Republican running against Franklin D. Roosevelt. He also led a concerted campaign to provide aid to China under the aegis of the United China Relief. After the war, HRL travelled extensively throughout Europe, Asia and the Middle East, advocating a tough stance against Communism. As a potent force in the Republican Party, HRL and his wife were early supporters of Dwight D. Eisenhower's candidacy for the presidency in 1952 and after the election, Clare Boothe Luce was appointed ambassador to Italy. As a result, HRL opened an office in Rome, splitting his time between Italy and the United States from 1953-1956. In 1954 he launched SPORTS ILLUSTRATED.
Throughout the 1950s and 1960s, in addition to his work at Time Inc, HRL was continuously involved in various charities related to the Presbyterian Church, Yale, and China, in addition to being a director, trustee, member, and sponsor of a large number of organizations. Becoming convinced that peace in the world could only be achieved by following the rule of law, he became a strong advocate for that concept. After marking the 40th anniversary of TIME in 1963, he retired from Time Inc. the following year. HRL continued to lecture and travel, as well as staying up-to-date with matters related to Time Inc. after his retirement until his death on 28 February 1967 in Phoenix, Arizona.
(The above note was based on various sources including, among others, Robert T. Elson, Time Inc: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941; Robert T. Elson,The World of Time Inc: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1941-1960; Curtis Prendergast and Geoffrey Colvin, The World of Time Inc: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1960-1980; Alan Brinkley, The Publisher: Henry Luce and His American Century; and documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Some materials (RC Box 1-18) are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Scope and Contents Note
The Henry R. Luce (hereafter HRL) papers include documents related to HRL's personal and professional life and which highlight his legacy as a major publisher and an active participant in public affairs of the 20th century. The collection includes extensive files with correspondence, memoranda and printed materials from and about publishers, members of the clergy, politicians, businessmen, editors, journalists, correspondents, ambassadors, officers and generals, judges, professors, college and university presidents, civil servants, foreign dignitaries, staff members of Time Inc., artists, writers, actors, movie producers and directors, lawyers, missionaries, friends of the Luce family from China and the United States, HRL's former schoolmates and professors, individuals HRL met while traveling, and various others.
In addition there are original drafts and finished versions of articles and speeches given at college convocations and commencements; Time Inc. anniversaries, lunches, and meetings; on radio stations; at award ceremonies; as interviews and testimony; and in front of various religious, civic, business, and professional groups. The articles include those written for LIFE, TIME, FORTUNE, and as book forewords. Of note are original letters written by HRL to his parents and siblings as a young man while living in China, traveling, and while attending school at Hotchkiss, Yale, and Chefoo.
There are also extensive domestic and international trip files; original awards given to HRL; reel audio tape recordings; correspondence, reports, and printed materials received from organizations and institutions HRL was involved with; checkbooks, bank statements, and other financial files; a large number of photographs of HRL as a child, with family members, working, relaxing, attending events, traveling, and with prominent individuals; and internal memoranda dealing with personnel, management, publishing and other issues involving Time Inc.
Subjects frequently found in HRL's speeches, articles, correspondence, and memoranda include international relations and world affairs, Communism and the Cold War, the rule of law and world peace through law, United States politics, public policy, his vision for the United States, the challenges and issues confronting the United States, the mission of the press, Asia and China, economics, religion, private enterprise, and World War II.
Some of the records are those of Clare Boothe Luce and consists primarily of her financial records, clippings, photographs, and subject files. Also included in the collection are records of Allen Grover, a longtime personal assistant to HRL and Vice President at Time Inc. These deal with his activities managing the personal and professional affairs of HRL, Clare Boothe Luce, and other members of the Luce family, as well as those of Time Inc.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift received with the records of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Archival Materials Note
For related materials at the New-York Historical Society please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009).
Some of Luce's papers are located in the Library of Congress as the Henry Robinson Luce papers, 1917-1967(MSS30767).
Related records may also be found at the Library of Congress in the Clare Boothe Luce papers, 1862-1997(MSS30759).
Check stubs; Bank statements.; Americans -- Foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, American; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Checkbooks; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Magazines (periodicals).; Periodicals -- Publishing.; Correspondence.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century.; China -- Description and travel.; Speeches (documents); Memorandums.; Letters (correspondence); Financial records.; Europe -- Description and travel -- 1919–1944; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Audiotapes; Journalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Press -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; World politics -- 20th century.; Communism; Cold War; International relations; Rule of law; Asia -- Description and travel; Photographs.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944; Luce (Family); Grover, Allen, 1900-1993; Time, inc.; United China Relief (U.S.); Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987
- Series I. Biographical and Subject Files, 1916-2004 (bulk, 1930-1967); 17.6 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic and is then further arranged chronologically. Miscellaneous files were included at the end of the alphabetical run. In addition, a small set of files labeled "personal" have been attached to the end of the series followed by another set of subject files.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series consists of files related to the life and legacy of Henry R. Luce (hereafter HRL) and includes correspondence and memoranda regarding awards given to HRL; updated drafts of his biography; letters marking his retirement from Time Inc. and letters of condolences following his death; reel recordings of HRL's speeches, interviews and the memorial services; remembrances and anecdotes of HRL from his coworkers and friends; calendar pages with his daily schedules; copies of financial ledgers; handwritten notes taken from HRL's desk; and various commemorative projects following his death, including a postage stamp and an exhibition at the Smithsonian Institution.
  The largest group of biographical files consists of HRL's trip files and includes internal correspondence and memoranda dealing with trip preparations; preliminary and final versions of itineraries and schedules; invitations to attend events while traveling and his responses; correspondence sent while traveling; letters of introduction; lists of individuals met while traveling and lists of individuals he expected to see, along with biographical information on them; and printed materials picked up while traveling, including guides, maps, and newspapers. There are also notes and reports giving HRL's impressions of the places visited, the political climate there, and his thoughts on the individuals met. Frequently these were sent to Time Inc. editors and officers for possible incorporation into articles. In addition, there are also notes and summaries from meetings with prominent individuals during his travels, including Charles de Gaulle and Clement Attlee.
  Miscellaneous files contain mostly copies of correspondence and memoranda assembled by year that deal with a wide variety of topics including management of LIFE, HRL's potential run for the Senate, and lobbying efforts by the Century Group to provide Great Britain with old U.S. destroyers during World War II. There are also additional organizational and subject files attached to the series that are similar to other such files found throughout the series with correspondence, memoranda, and printed materials with or about organizations in which HRL was involved as a sponsor or beneficiary, served on a committee or council, and was a trustee or board member. In addition these files contain correspondence, memoranda, background and research materials pertaining to HRL's outside interests and activities including China and the rule of law.
  Access Restrictions
  The reel tapes in this series are restricted due to a lack of availability of the necessary playback equipment and current lack of a surrogate version.
  - Art Collection, 1956-1965, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes lists of paintings owned by HRL and the paper "The Luce Family and American Art."
  - Awards - General, 1937-1940, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes a certificate conferring the title and privileges of Socius Emeritus on HRL, awarded by the Louisiana Club of Houston, Texas.
  - Awards - General, 1947-1953, 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes a photograph of the insignia of the Order of Orange-Nassau. Correspondents include L. Fritz Gruber.
  - Awards - General, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards - General, 1957, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes a telegram from Igor I. Sikorsky.
  - Awards - General, 1958-1960, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes a certificate from the United States Naval War College and an official citation from The Architectural League of New York. Also includes a commemorative booklet of The Research Instititute of America's Living History Award Dinner.
  - Awards - General, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes photographs of the "Key Man" award from the Avenue of the Americas Association and group shots with HRL at the award presentation event.
  - Awards - General, 1962, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes a certificate from the San Francisco Area World Trade Association.
  - Awards - General, 1963-1967, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes a certificate titled "Wisdom Award of Honor" presented to HRL by Wisdom Magazine and The Wisdom Society; a letter from Thomas J. Watson Jr. to Hedley Donovan regarding the endorsement of HRL for the Freedom Medal; certificate from Syracuse University in connection with awarding Luce the School of Journalism's Medal for Distinguished Service to Journalism; and a photograph of the illuminated resolution scroll awarded by the Magazine Publishers Association, Inc.
  - Awards - Miscellaneous, 1946-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes lists of HRL's awards and honorary degrees.
  - Awards - Forbes Magazine Thirtieth Anniversary Banquet to Honor Today's Fifty Foremost Business Leaders, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes a souvenir program and an autographed caricature of B.C. Forbes in a kilt. Correspondents include B. C. Forbes and Malcolm Forbes.
  - Awards - Forbes Magazine Fortieth Anniversary Banquet to Honor Today's Fifty Foremost Business Leaders, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes a souvenir program. Correspondents include Bruce C. Forbes.
  - Awards - The Progress Medal of the Photographic Society of America, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Correspondents include Henry M. Lester.
  - Awards - American Bar Association (ABA) Silver Gavel, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Awards - Advertising Club of Washington D.C., 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes memoranda regarding early FORTUNE research on the story "Changing American Tastes."
  - Awards - Socratic Medal of the Order of Ahepa, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes photographs of the award and of individuals posing next to a clay model of the award.
  - Awards - Magazine Publishing Association's Henry John Fisher Award, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes photographs of individuals mingling around a food table in an outside setting and of Ray Sullivan holding a photo camera.
  - Awards - The Robins Awards of America, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Awards - Hamilton College, 1961 October (Offsite-box RC18, Folder 6)
    Contains a film reel.
  - Awards - Originals (folder 1 of 2), 1939-1965 (Box 181, Folder 5)
    Includes the Overseas Press Club of America Special Award, certificate designating HRL an honorary citizen of Oskaloosa, Iowa, the American Institute of Architects certificate of honorary membership, the Architectural League of New York President's Medal Award, notification from the University of Missouri School of Journalism on being elected as an honorary chairman for its fiftieth anniversary with a large number of "freedom of the press" stamps, the Henry Johnson Fisher Award from the Magazine Publishers Association with a photo of a crystal cup, and an original Senate of the State of Texas resolution expressing the appreciation of the people of Texas for an article in LIFE.
  - Awards - Originals (folder 2 of 2) - oversize, 1952-1956 (Box OS-Small)
    Contains the Drexel Institute of Technology Business Administration Award and a citation for the Franklin Award for Distinguished Service.
  - Bible Sent to HRL by Briton Hadden (folder 1 of 2), 1924, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains a note from Hadden to HRL.
  - Bible Sent to HRL by Briton Hadden (folder 2 of 2), 1924 (Offsite-box RC18)
    Contains The Old Testament by James Moffatt.
  - Biographical Information on HRL (folder 1 of 2), 1936-2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes different versions of HRL biographies and timelines, and a passport application. Also includes obituaries for his first wife, Lila Hotz Luce Tyng, and sister Elisabeth Luce Moore.
  - Biographical Information on HRL (folder 2 of 2), 1936-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Books About or Involving HRL, 1942-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes memoranda dealing with a proposal to publish a book of HRL speeches and a search for an author to write his biography. Correspondents include Gerald Walker and Joe David Brown (copies).
  - Books and Book Reviews, 1946-1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes HRL's notes "Communist Manifesto" possibly made at the United States Senatorial Committee on the Judiciary Analysis of the Khrushchev Speech of January 6, 1961. Hearing and book reviews possibly written by HRL.
  - Center for Cultural and Technical Interchange Between East and West, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes a summary of HRL's statements made during lunch with Arthur Goodfriend.
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Commission on Race and Housing, 1957-1958 (Box 182, Folder 5)
    Includes a copy of a memo from Emmie Nollen analyzing the draft report of the Commission on Race and Housing.
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Pacem in Terris (2 folders), 1963-1967 (Box 182, Folder 6-7)
    Includes an original draft of a possible article from Cory to Applegate, original printed materials from the Pacem in Terris Convocation, copies of possible speeches and correspondence from Hedley Donovan, and the softcover book Peace on Earth (Pacem in Terris) edited by Edward Reed.
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Miscellaneous (Box 183, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of memoranda dealing with the Race and Housing Commission and copies of correspondence with Robert M. Hutchins.
  - China Institute and China House, 1944-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes the speech delivered by HRL at the dedication ceremony of China House on August 27, 1944.
  - China - Associated Boards for Christian Colleges in China, 1935-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - China - United China Relief (2 folders), 1939-1950, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Name of the organization later changed to "United Service to China." Includes a memorandum from Douglas Auchincloss to HRL describing a meeting with Peal S. Buck and copies of correspondence from Pearl S. Buck, Herbert Hoover, Cordell Hull, and Joseph Kennedy.
  - China - Yale-in-China, 1946-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - China - Miscellaneous (3 folders), 1941-1968, 1986-1995 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
    Includes a memorandum on a meeting with YMCA leaders in Shanghai, the article "Henry Luce - One of the Men Behind the Scenes of American Imperialism," and HRL's comments on a draft of the "Study Paper on China" by the United Presbyterian Church in the USA.